<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Random Reasons &amp; Reflections - Data Science</title><link href="https://ojon.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://ojon.github.io/feeds/data-science.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://ojon.github.io/</id><updated>2018-07-23T16:00:00-03:00</updated><entry><title>Introduction to Data Science with a Mnemonic Image</title><link href="https://ojon.github.io/aboutDataScience.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-07-23T16:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2018-07-23T16:00:00-03:00</updated><author><name>João Oda</name></author><id>tag:ojon.github.io,2018-07-23:/aboutDataScience.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;!-- Summary: Whats is Data Science about. --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another day I found on the web this curious drawing (clearly inspired on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mega_Man"&gt;megaman&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure width=600&gt;
  &lt;img src="https://pre00.deviantart.net/c0d7/th/pre/i/2010/134/e/5/rpn_005_dice_man_by_jecht_striker.jpg" alt="DiceMan" &gt;
  &lt;figcaption style="text-align:right" &gt;drawing credits to VR-Hyoumaru&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's take a look at this picture and do some associations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dices are one the main symbols of &lt;strong&gt;probability theory&lt;/strong&gt;, a field of &lt;strong&gt;mathematics&lt;/strong&gt; that with many applications and that provides the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;!-- Summary: Whats is Data Science about. --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another day I found on the web this curious drawing (clearly inspired on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mega_Man"&gt;megaman&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure width=600&gt;
  &lt;img src="https://pre00.deviantart.net/c0d7/th/pre/i/2010/134/e/5/rpn_005_dice_man_by_jecht_striker.jpg" alt="DiceMan" &gt;
  &lt;figcaption style="text-align:right" &gt;drawing credits to VR-Hyoumaru&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's take a look at this picture and do some associations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dices are one the main symbols of &lt;strong&gt;probability theory&lt;/strong&gt;, a field of &lt;strong&gt;mathematics&lt;/strong&gt; that with many applications and that provides the foundations to &lt;strong&gt;statistics&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here I will associate the robot with &lt;strong&gt;automation&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;computation&lt;/strong&gt; (although other fields like mechatronics might come to your mind).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me add some extra piece of information. In Portuguese the word "dados" can mean &lt;strong&gt;data&lt;/strong&gt;, but it can also means dices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now imagine whatever our "data/dice man" mission is, it ll be in an &lt;strong&gt;environment&lt;/strong&gt;, a &lt;strong&gt;context&lt;/strong&gt; and the more he knows about it, better will be outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am about to introduce the field of &lt;strong&gt;Data Science&lt;/strong&gt; and maybe these associations and a mental picture will help you memorize the concept, a trick I find useful in many situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What's Data Science About?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years the term &lt;strong&gt;Data Science&lt;/strong&gt; has emerged to nominate a interdisciplinary area of knowledge. Data scientists and other professionals of this area provides organizations with some form of analytics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;descriptive analytics&lt;/strong&gt; can show some insights and point out hidden information, you need to analyze these and see how they can affect your business decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;predictive analytics&lt;/strong&gt; uses models to predict an outcome that extrapolates the information we have until now, in many cases is predict the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &lt;strong&gt;prescriptive analytics&lt;/strong&gt; you careful select your optimization metric and you will use data to decide what actions take to maximize your metric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Summary for me Data Science is about &lt;strong&gt;obtain value from data&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data science is closely related with &lt;em&gt;Big Data&lt;/em&gt; phenomena. To deal with massive amounts of data we need to employ computational tools guided by statistical and math principles with in a business context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I will borrow from &lt;a href="http://berkeleysciencereview.com/how-to-become-a-data-scientist-before-you-graduate/"&gt;berkeleysciencereview&lt;/a&gt; (right now, working on item 9 from the link) a more common info-graphic that summarizes this idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="infograph" src="http://i.imgur.com/aoz1BJy.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In order to be effective, be careful!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must know the rules of the game that you are playing. In Data Science you need &lt;strong&gt;domain expertise&lt;/strong&gt;. You don't need to be an expert in the field but at least communicate with the other professionals that will help you with insights and what is relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You come up with a list of questions, you might attempt answer with data, but before put &lt;em&gt;analytics&lt;/em&gt; effort on it, it is wise to find out what questions, if answered, &lt;strong&gt;add more value to the business&lt;/strong&gt;. Maybe it's the case you don't even have the data yet. Does it worth enhance the accuracy of a model by 0.1% or better move to another questions. Is &lt;em&gt;accuracy&lt;/em&gt; the best way to evaluate the answer to your problem?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &lt;em&gt;prescriptive analytics&lt;/em&gt; you need careful select your optimization metric in order to &lt;strong&gt;match your values&lt;/strong&gt;, otherwise you may end in an undesired point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to &lt;strong&gt;know you data&lt;/strong&gt;, the threats to your analysis and limitations. As unfair coins and dices, you data might have bias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other perspectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a field that is still maturing, you will come across multiple definitions. I will leave you now with some from Columbia professors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9"&gt;
  &lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/a8abc9SgVUM" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I borrow this video from edX MOOC I have done "DS101X: Statistical Thinking for Data Science and Analytics"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final considerations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have interest in AI in general and one of the main things I like about Data Science is that it brings AI, especially machine learning to daily practical use. Most of times it will be in a pervasive way, but it's there.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope now you may have a better idea of one of the main topics of this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="data science"></category><category term="intro"></category><category term="beginner"></category><category term="AI"></category><category term="ML"></category></entry></feed>